Never forget why you are the church.
Officially, so we're going to go ahead and get started tonight.
Happy, Lord, say amen.
Hey man, once again, a good crowd.
Ronnie, they have an event at their church tonight,
and then also Sunday night, next week.
So they will not be joining us.
The good thing is, is that I've been talking with Ronnie a
little bit about their plans, and it looks like they're going to have a spring semester.
and do something very similar in their church.
So it'd be cool if next semester in January, we
could maybe have another church kind of come in, do the same thing that
Ronnie's church was doing, and try to grow this thing.
So that'd be exciting.
For example, I've had about two or three meetings with other churches about
getting something like this started in their own church, and a lot
of times, it's like they like it, and I say, Okay, so what's the plan?
They're like, well
we're gonna have a grill out.
And I'm just like, that's not, that's not what I, that's not the two
hour conversation we just had.
But it's hard to get out of the mindset that
we've really had for a long time of what men's ministry is.
And so that's why we're talking about this, not in the form of men's
ministry, but in the forms of men's discipleship.
And so, it's just semantics, but words do matter.
All right?
So let's pray, and we'll get right into it.
Father we thank you, Lord, for this night.
God, we just thank you for the group of men here, God, that they're
here intentionally to learn from you, God, to disciple, and also be discipled.
So God, give me the words to say at tonight's lesson,
and for all those that are not able to make it, God,
I pray that you just blessed them as well.
God, we thank you, we love you, just name, pray.
Amen.
Go ahead and turn your Bibles to Deuteronomy, chapter 6, Deuteronomy,
chapter 6, that is in the Old Testament.
1st 5 books.
Anyone know what the 1st 5 books are called?
The law, Torah.
Yeah, okay, nice.
We're talking about a man and his fatherhood tonight.
Um, you cannot talk about fatherhood without
talking about manhood.
Psalm 121 says, help, Lord,
for the godly man ceases.
Proverbs 20, verse 6 through 7 says most men will
proclaim each his own goodness, but who can find a faithful man?
The righteous man walks in his integrity, his children are
blessed after him.
That question there should echo in our minds who
can find a faithful man.
What does it mean to be faithful?
What it means to be faithful is to be established and trustworthy.
The word faithful comes from the word that means to
build up support and foster.
In other words, men are established, but are we faithfully established?
Are we established in the faith, right?
We've seen a whole bunch about how men are just men, right?
We see someone come in and they never want to change and
never want to do anything different, what they've always done, and we excuse
them by saying, well, that's just so and so.
Right?
And what we're saying there is, they are established in such a
way that is not God glorifying, and as the godly
men in the church, what we're saying is, we're just okay with it.
Y'alls, listen, that's the question in Proverbs 20.
Who can find a faithful man?
In other words, this building, this supporting,
this fostering has established one to be firm or faithful,
one that you can trust or believe, one that is moral,
thus one that is faithful, but
a faithful man who can find.
Again, that word fine, very, very clearly, to come forth, to appear,
or exist, it means to occur, to meet or to be present.
Right?
We need men that are present.
We need men that are at the forefront of what's
going on, not just at church, but in the home.
I personally believe that we are not only called to build godly boys
and girls that are our own children, but as men, I believe
that we are also called to build godly boys and godly girls that
are not our children.
We need to be ministering to everyone that God puts in our midst.
For example, we got kids here at the church that they don't have a godly daddy.
They just don't.
Their dad does not care a thing in the world about the things of God.
Listen, hey, we don't just sit there and say, oh, poor them.
No, we show them what a godly father looks like.
That's part of manhood.
That's part of fatherhood.
Proverbs 25, 19, confidence in an unfaithful
man in time of trouble is like a bad tooth and a foot out of joint.
In other words, you can't depend on any of it.
It's painful.
In 1980, Carl Wilson.
He wrote a book called Our Dance Has Turned to Death, but
we can renew the family and nations.
very long title.
But it was about notes
that a degrading culture
displays, and there's seven typical characteristics,
and I want to see if you think that our society or culture
has these characteristics.
First off, men reject spiritual and moral development as
the leaders of families.
In other words, they're okay with where they are.
They don't want to ever get any closer to God.
They're just fine.
If I come to church, I'll come to church.
We're good, I'll go home, everything's fine.
Check off the list.
Number two, men begin to neglect their families in search of material gain.
So in other words, we're all about what we can earn.
We want the next dollar, right?
Number three, men begin to engage in adulterous relationships
of homosexual sex.
Listen, that's all over our culture today.
You can't open Facebook without that happening.
You can't open, or you can't watch the news without someone
coming out or somebody saying, hey, you know, look at
this parade or look at this, this, this, this organization.
It's all exactly what we just said there.
Number four, women begin to devalue the role of motherhood and homemaker.
See, we're in a culture right now to where we think that homemaking
is a degrading position.
That's not a degrading position.
That's a very godly position for a woman.
Number five, husbands and wives begin to complete or sorry,
compete with each other, and families disintegrate.
Number six, selfish individualism fragments society
into warring factions.
And number seven, men and women lose faith in God and reject all authority
over their lives.
I don't know about you guys, but that sounds like the culture we live in today.
Listen, soon, moral anarchy reigns, and when the family collapses,
the society soon follows.
A nation is only as strong as the families that make it.
So as men of God, as men who
are fathers, and maybe you're here and you're not a father yet, listen, hey,
when you become a father, we need to know this stuff.
We need godly fathers.
We need every man to stand in the midst of the
decay of culture, and there's 3 places that we got to stand.
Number one, we must stand before the Father in heaven.
Deuteronomy chapter 6, one and two.
It says this.
Now, these are the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments that the,
which the Lord your God commanded to teach you, that you might do them
in the land, whether you go to possess it, that
thou mightest fear the Lord thy God, to keep all his statues, and his commandments,
which I command thee, thou and thy son, and thy son, son,
all the days of thy life, that thy days may be prolonged.
We see in verse 4 and 5.
Hear, O Israel, the Lord, our God, is one Lord, and thou shalt love the Lord
thy God, with all thine heart, with all thine soul,
and with all thy might.
He must stand before the Father in heaven, loving
God with all your heart, soul, and might is a non-negotiable.
He will accept no excuses.
You know what we've done in the church?
We've accepted mediocrity and lukewarm faith.
And God rejects it.
So let's put this in a perspective here.
In the church today, we have accepted what God rejects.
No wonder it's not working.
Men, the only one who can keep you from loving God with all your heart, soul,
and mind, or your might is yourself.
There's no other excuse.
You can't blame it on your wife because she always nags and complains.
You can't blame it on your kids because they always, you know, take
your attention and this and that and your money, all the things.
The only person that's going to take you from loving
the Lord God with all your heart, soul and might is you.
The truth is, you will not be a good leader unless you are a great follower.
Listen, it's funny.
My daughter, she's catching on to the fact that
I'm a pastor of a church.
I mean, she has for a little bit, but it's really kind of just getting, you
know, a little bit annoying now.
So she'll say things.
I'll say, we were coming to church on Wednesday
and she got out the car.
She didn't have no have no shoes.
And I'm like, baby, where are your shoes at?
She's like, well, I didn't know we were coming to the church.
So I was like, well, it's Wednesday night.
Like we go to church and stuff.
And I literally, I said, you got to have shoes when you go to the house.
And that's what she said, she, it doesn't matter.
Your pastor anyway.
I don't need shoes.
And I'm like, 1st off, I don't even know what that means.
Like, what does that mean, right?
Like, is this holy ground or something?
don't understand.
But here's the thing.
Listen, just because I'm pastor, she doesn't need to need
to see me just as the person who stands in front of people and tells people what to do.
She's got to see me following Jesus.
That's the most important part of my father, her, is
that she sees me as a great follower.
Listen, a great leader, cool.
I hope that happens, but a great follower of Christ, that's the most important.
And so here in the text, the Bible teaches when a man gets serious about
following God with his whole heart.
God desires not only poor out his blessing on that man, but
on his children and his grandchildren.
Mark 834, and when he had called the people unto him with
his disciples also, he said unto them, whatsoever, I'm sorry,
whosoever will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his
cross, and follow me.
It is very simple.
Every father doesn't matter who you are.
You are either one of 2 things, self centered or god centered.
Self-centered, God-centered.
And God's, listen, I've been self-centered.
That's my default mode in the flesh, you understand what I'm saying?
It's all about me.
It's what I it's not what I want.
It's my comfort, it's my convenience.
It's my ambitions.
It's my desires.
But see, when you become God centered, it's all about what he wants in your life.
And that's not always the easiest thing, but it is simple.
Just follow him.
Man, how would your how would your families describe you?
We stand before a holy God, the Father in heaven.
May we grasp, and come to realize that our life has always lived before him.
He is ever before us, and we are always living before him.
And we might be able to hide things from our wife, our children,
even our friends, but men we cannot and will not be able to hide anything from
our heavenly Father as hard as we try to do so.
How we live before the Father will ultimately affect how we live before our family.
So we see that we stand before the Father, but
also we stand before the family at home.
Deuteronomy 6, verse 2, and verses 6 through 7.
We've already read verse 2.
It says this in 6 to 7.
And these words, which I command thee, this day shall be in thine heart, and thou
shalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them
when thou sittest thine house, and when thou walkest by the way,
and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.
There's a few there's a few areas where we got to stand before the family at home.
First off in our walk.
Colossians 2, 6 through 10, it talks about,
as ye therefore have received Christ, Jesus, the Lord, so walk ye in him.
That is an ongoing pattern of walking with Jesus.
Not just on Sunday, not just on Wednesday when you have time,
but an ongoing pattern of walking with the Lord.
And what does that look like?
Well, 1st off, we walk with consistent value.
What do you value as a man?
Because here's the here's the long and the short.
What you value as a man will control your behavior.
What you see is the most important, what you see is priority and life.
What you see as what matters is what you're gonna live for.
Values, control behavior.
We act on the basis of what we believe really matters what
is right and good.
And whoever influences the core values in your group is, in fact, the leader.
You want to see a leader of someone who is dictating
and influencing the culture of whatever group you're talking about.
So listen to me.
If you don't like the culture of your home, it's not your wife's fault, not
your kid's fault, it's your fault.
That process must begin with the value values that God
instills in the leader, but also we're to walk with a clear vision.
Proverbs 2918, where there is no vision, the people perish.
Vision calls the believer.
Great vision precedes great achievement.
Vision is a clear mental picture of what could be fueled
by the conviction that it should be.
In other words, listen, we can sit right here as a men's as a men's
discipleship group and try to look to the future, maybe having a men's
summit in Wilson County with 500 men, and we have to rent
out the Expo Center.
We have a big, you know, big worship team and we have all these these
breakout sessions and all the things that I would love to see in our county.
But listen, hey, visioning is fun, but we
have to have the conviction that it needs to happen.
And if we have the conviction that it has to happen.
Guess what?
We'll have the boldness to make the work put in the work to make it happen.
So great vision precedes great achievement.
If you can't see what God has for your family, then how are you ever gonna achieve it?
Walk with a clear vision.
What is the vision you have for your family?
Oh, well, I wanna pay off my car.
What?
That's great.
That's good.
Okay?
And be financially competent.
But vision goes far further than that.
So what is the vision for your family?
So what a clear vision, but also walk with a critical verse.
There's a bunch of, listen, I could name verse
at the verse at the verse.
Do you have a life verse?
This convicted me.
Do I have a life verse?
1 Timothy 412 is one of my favorite verses ever because I'm young.
I want to be an example in all that I do.
I want people to be able to look at me, including my wife and kid and say,
that is what a Christ follower should look like.
People say, oh, well, John 316, listen, that's great, and that's awesome.
But I'm talking about a life verse that you say, I want to live by this.
This is what this verse is convicting to me.
Verse compels the burden.
Have you ever been reading something that you've read over and over again,
and maybe you're coming to it again, and you read a verse
that you know you know, but all of a sudden, man, it just hits you in such a different new way.
Same words, same text, same chapter,
same verse, but it hits you in such a way that you're like, man, I never saw that before.
Verse compels the burden.
The word must be come flesh and dwell among my wife and children
in church and community.
In other words, we are to live out the word.
There's the old saying that what if the only Bible
anyone ever read was the way you live for Christ, what would they learn about Jesus?
Man, that's convicting.
We'd rather just give them a little New Testament and Psalms
and Proverbs and say, go on, and I want to just do your own thing.
No, sometimes we got a show and lead.
So we see that with a stand in my walk, in our walk, but
also, uh, with looking at the wife as well.
Genesis 2.24, therefore shall man leave his father and mother and shall
Cleveland to his wife, and they shall be one flesh.
So it's not just our want.
We stand before the family at home, not just with our walk, but also with our wife.
Some people can't communicate.
And anyone in here struggle with communication.
Uh-huh.
Most men do.
I mean, that's just the, listen, if you never, if you never
had a couple in, in an office sitting on a couch and you're sitting behind
a desk and you try to figure things out, you realize, man, men are bad at communicating.
You kind of become an interpreter, okay, listen, what he just said here was this, right?
And he's like, yeah, that's exactly what I said.
I'm like, yeah, but it wasn't at all, right?
A woman told the lawyer she wanted a divorce and the lawyer
question says, does your husband have a grudge?
She said, no, he has a carport.
The lawyer asked, do you have grounds?
She answered positively, yes, about about 5 acres.
The lawyer asked pointedly, what's the problem?
The lady answered, we can't communicate.
Folks, listen, that's a lot of times how we live in our life.
We sit here and we say different things and we think that we're getting we're
getting it to the point, but we're really not communicating at all.
As the family shepherd, we have to lead her.
Ephesians 523 for the husband is the head
of the wife, even as Christ is the head of the church and he is the savior of the body.
As the family shepherd, we are to love her.
Ephesians 525
Husbands love your wives, even as Christ also loved the church and gave himself for it.
As the family shepherd.
We have to lift her.
1 Peter 3, 7.
Husbands likewise dwell with them with understanding,
giving honor to the wife as to the weaker vessel, and as
being heirs together, the grace of God, that your prayers may not be hindered.
Notice it says, dwell with them with understanding.
How often do we just refuse to understand their point
of view or perspective or their pain or sorrow, whatever they're going through?
We say, well, it doesn't matter to me, so I
don't even know what you're saying right now.
Right?
Like my wife would tell me something about a deal at Sam's.
And I'm like, man, it goes in one ear and out the other.
And then she's like, man, do you even care what I care about?
I'm like, yeah.
Right?
And, and, but I, I need to.
Everyone hates everyone hates the fair for some reason, right?
My wife is one of those that she's stinking, loves the fair.
I'm talking.
She go every single day.
I mean, let me say, she dragged me to that fair 3 times in the past 10 days.
I mean, I ruined, like, 3 shirts and sweat, and I'm just talking, it was terrible, but you know what?
had a great time.
And and 2 of those 3 times, I got real cranky right there at
the end and got convicted of me, convicted me of it later on.
I told her, I said, I'll burn this place down if you ever bring me here again.
Right, at least I didn't go on swings.
Yeah.
Yeah, that was crazy.
But what I'm trying to say is, listen, we had to understand them, giving
honor to the wife as the weaker vest one as being heirs
together, the grace of life, that your prayers may not be hindered.
So we look at, we stand before our family with our
walk, with our wife, but also with our wealth.
Psalm 127 through 5 says, Behold, children are a heritage from the Lord.
The fruit of the womb is a reward, like arrows in the hand of a warrior,
so are the children of one's youth.
Happy is the man who has his quiver full of them.
They shall not be ashamed, but shall speak with their enemies in the gate.
Deuteronomy 6, verse 2, we've already read it, but
I'll read it again.
It says that thou mightest fear the Lord, thy God, to keep all
his statues, and his commandments would I command thee, thou and thy son
and thy son's son.
All the days of our life and that thy days may be prolonged.
Ephesians 64, and you fathers do not provoke your children or
rap, but bring them up in the training and admonition of the Lord.
Proverbs 22 verse 6, train up a child in the way that he should go,
and when he is old, he will not depart from it.
You know, this is a hard one for me.
Because when you passed it for almost 10 years, you see
a whole lot of kids grow up and stuff, And
a lot of people have told me and said, well, well, preacher, I,
you know, I had my kid in church.
You know, I made sure that they had a Bible, and I made
sure they went to camp, and I made sure, and I try to train them
in the right way, but why are they going wayward?
Now, it's a very sensitive topic, and I understand
because it's very difficult.
But let me ask you something.
Take church away.
Where is their training in the Lord?
Don't get me wrong.
Church is important.
But remember, church is to come alongside you.
not to be the sole provider of your spiritual well-being.
So in other words, what we've done in a whole generation of kids,
and maybe multiple generations of kids.
Is we said, oh, I'm going to raise them in the way that they should go.
I'm going to have them in church on Sunday morning if we don't have anything else better going on.
And then we genuinely wonder why they don't love the Lord when they grow up.
It's heartbreaking.
I can tell you that the way that you live at
home is way more important the way that you sit in a Pewit church.
You can raise your hand to the Lord all you want on Sunday.
But if you're not walking with the Lord Monday through Saturday,
guess what, guess what they're going to see more of.
That's not confusing, that's clarifying.
That's telling them that, hey, this is all just a show.
If the home is truly Christian, it is a place of encouragement in such
a home, the child finds refuge from battles.
And yet strength to fight the battles and carry the burdens of growing maturity.
He finds a loving heart, a watching eye, a listening ear and a helping hand.
He does not want any other place, home meets his needs.
In this kind of a home, it is natural for a child to trust Christ and want to live for him.
You know, I have a vision of how I want my
daughters to be when they grow up.
And I understand everyone that has grown kids.
You're scoffing right now like, oh, yeah, we'll see how that works out.
But I've gotten into the habit of writing my daughter's
letters sporadically.
And I haven't given them to them.
Obviously, only one can read and not that good.
But anyway, but it's for circumstances when
they really don't want to talk to me.
They really don't want to, it's like dad's not cool anymore.
I want them to see that long time ago, uh,
they were on my heart and I prepare for this moment.
And so I've got letters like what happens when her
heart gets broken from a 1st crush.
Right?
As much as that angers the mess out of me right now, I know what's gonna happen.
You understand what I'm saying?
And so if it's something to where, hey, you
know, maybe she's got her door closed and you say, oh, well, my house,
you know, my kids aren't gonna close their doors yet, whatever, dude.
You know what I'm saying?
Maybe she has her door closed.
She doesn't want daddy to come in.
You know, all I got to do is just put that letter under her door and just kind of push
and say, I just, I prepare for this moment, because I loved you way before this moment.
Now listen, that's just one little part.
And I haven't had to use a letter yet, praise God, right?
I just beat up the kindergartners that like my daughter.
You know what I'm saying?
But either way, listen, hey, a Christian home is cultivated starting now.
starting now.
If you want your kids to be sharp spiritually, then you better be sharp spiritually.
Christian discipleship begins at home.
The church is a partner.
Sunday school is a partner, but men, the responsibility is ours.
See, many parents are more concerned about their career instead of their children,
their finances instead of their family, their houses instead of their homes.
And listen, homes and finances and careers, it's all important.
It's all part of it.
As a matter of fact, Proverbs 13, 22 says,
a good man leaves an inheritance to his children's children.
Listen, if you got young children, especially, you didn't be thinking about the inheritance, you're going to leave them.
Both material and spiritual.
And here's a fact, you can lose your family without getting a divorce.
You can be there and your family be gone.
Joseph Hall says Satan rocks the cradle when we sleep at our devotions.
So we stand before the Father, stand before the family, and before we get to
our table time, number three,
we stand before the future that's here.
Deuteronomy 6, verse 2, and 3.
Again, it says, here, therefore, arrears you, and observe to do it, that
it may be well with thee, that you may increase mightily
as the Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee, and the land that floweth with
milk, and honey.
Deuteronomy 30, verse 11, it says, I call heaven and earth as
witnesses today against you that I have set before you life and death blessing and cursing.
Therefore, choose life.
That both you and your descendants may live, skip into verse
20, that you may love the Lord your God, that you may obey his voice,
that you may cling to him, and he is your life in the length of your
days, and that you may dwell in a land which the Lord swore to
your fathers, to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob to give them.
As we have seen in the text, the Christian home is called to develop
the lives of many, it is a non-negotiable.
Your family is only one link in the chain that has brought you to this day.
This link of today is also preparing the next link in the future.
In 1980, James Dobson said, the husbands of our nation
holds the key to the well being of the family.
How did that go?
How is that going?
Families drip because they lack male leadership.
Today, more than ever, our kids are getting foggy messages about
what is right and what is wrong.
Psalm 127 3 through 5, it is a non-negotiable.
I must shape my arrows.
I must sharpen my arrows.
I must shoot my arrows.
So as you follow Christ, you cut a path of clarity that they
can step through and follow in your first steps.
There's nothing more than confusion, the confusing directions.
Have you ever tried to put together something that you bought for real cheap?
And it's like the directions, it's like, hey, you should have 10
things to put this together and 3 of them in a box.
That's the most annoying and frustrating thing ever.
Listen, how do you think our kids feel when they sit there and
they're looking for a way to live life?
They're looking for discipleship.
They may not know how to ask it.
They may not have to put it in words, but they're looking for their father
to lead them, and we refuse to do so.
Listen, that is confusing.
That's disappointing.
They need clarity.
This is what a godly person does.
This is what a godly person does not do.
You say, well, I don't want to force my kids in a church.
Listen, hey, we're already losing 75% of them.
Whether we force them or not, I'd rather them be under the gospel as much
as I can have control over that.
You lead a family for a 100 years by following Jesus Christ today with your whole heart.
The man of God is the greatest evidence
for or against Christianity.
A man and his fatherhood.
Father, as we go into Our
table times, God, I pray, Lord, you just give us vulnerability,
God, God, I pray that any pride or ego.
Well, no matter if there's men here who have kids, don't
have kids, I don't know there's people here that got kids
that have gone wayward, Lord, they're broken hearted about.
So God, I pray, Lord, that you just are able to give us the words to
say, God, so we can open up and not just be discipled,
but also disciple others, God.
God, we thank you, Lord.
We thank you being the heavenly Father that we have an
example of so we can be the loving Father for our family.
Since you just ain't praying.
And everybody said,